All right. There was this black preacher guy in the subway in
the A-train. You know you're on a train and it's crowded and
somebody starts doing their thing. He said, 'I never saw a U-Haul
following a hearse.'
You never saw a hearse. You know, he was giving a thing
about, you know, you can't take it with you, right? But it
was a beautiful image. That's good. All right. Good morning. I'm Dan
Marioff. I'm filling in for Lindsey while he is at the IRF
conference, I think for the next two days. And we are on
ע"ג עמוד א' Ayin Gimel Amud Aleph a bit ahead, where on
the second wide line. And before we get into the גמרא, Gemara,
since we have a little bit of time, I just wanted to
bring one of the main, the main מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim about
some of the topics that's come up here, which is a question
of ספק. safek. Question of when there are cases of doubt, how
do you פסקן? pasken? Possibly the most far-reaching and central סוגיה sugya
to פסק psak in practical cases and in terms of how to
navigate מחלוקת machlokes and all sorts of things like that. And the
first important source is from the רמב"ם. Rambam. The רמב"ם Rambam at
the end of the ninth פרק perek of הלכות טומאת מת, Hilchos
Tumas Meis, interesting place. It's interesting to me that all of the
laws of ספק, safek, at least for the most part, find their
voice in the world of טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. That's because learned
from סוטה, Sotah, there's a principle applied to טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah,
which is ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים טהור. safek tumah b'reshus harabbim tahor.
If there's some kind of a source of impurity that is doubtful,
like maybe the שרץ sheretz is alive, maybe the שרץ sheretz is
dead, and it's found in a public space. Interestingly that רשות הרבים
reshus harabbim for טומאה tumah is defined just as three people and
not as what we would call sort of halachic רשות הרבים reshus
harabbim normally for הלכות שבת Hilchos Shabbos or something like that in
terms of carrying.
So in the case of רשות הרבים, reshus harabbim, ספק טומאה safek
tumah would be טהור. tahor. We follow more lenient ruling, but in
a רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid, ספק טומאה safek tumah is טמא. tamei.
So that's the first sort of set of rules about ספק, safek,
and that's both of those rules are within the דאורייתא D'oraisa world.
And then as it comes to ספק דאורייתא safek D'oraisa compared to
ספק דרבנן safek D'rabbanan by all other kinds of הלכות halachos besides
טומאה, tumah, we have the general rule: ספק דאורייתא לחומרא. safek D'oraisa
l'chumra. With biblical laws, we follow the more stringent possibility of the
doubt, and in a case of rabbinic law, we could rely on
the more lenient possibility in a case of doubt. Now Charlie's a
statistician, so he can talk all about this statistical side of things.
And here we're talking about very simple doubts often, you know, is...
I don't know, maybe in certain cases, well maybe you could figure
it out and you wouldn't apply the same kinds of rules. The
רמב"ם Rambam right at the end of of the ninth פרק perek
of הלכות טומאת מת Hilchos Tumas Meis says: דבר ידוע, davar yadua,
everybody knows this, שכל אלו הטומאות וכיוצא בהן שהן משום ספק הרי
הן של דבריהם. she-kol elu ha-tumaos v'kayotzei bahen she-hein mishum safek hare
hein shel divreihem. Anything that we're concerned about because of doubt about
טומאה tumah according to the רמב"ם Rambam is only rabbinic itself. That
means that the principle of being concerned about a doubtful case is
itself only a rabbinic law. And the רמב"ם Rambam continues: ואין טמאין
מן התורה אלא מי שנטמא בטומאה ודאית. v'ein t'me'in min ha-Torah ela
mi she-nitma b'tumah vada'is. The only טומאה tumah at the biblical level
is if it was for sure טמא. tamei. And he goes on:
אבל כל הספקות, aval kol ha-s'fekos, and then he continues: בטומאות בין
במאכלות אסורות בין בעריות ושבתות, b'tumaos bein b'machalos asuros bein b'arayos v'shabbasos,
any different realm of הלכה halacha you want, טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah
or foods, what we would call איסור והיתר, issur v'heter, עריות, arayos,
even in cases as stringent as עריות, arayos, sexual relationships, like we
see here, and שבתות, shabbasos, keeping שבת Shabbos and holidays, any kind
of ספק, safek, the רמב"ם Rambam says: אין חוששין להם אלא מדברי
סופרים. ein chosheshin lahem ela mi-divrei sofrim. If there's a case of
doubt, according to the רמב"ם Rambam that immediately bumps it down to
a rabbinic prohibition. Question. Yes.
So that would have halachic consequences in that you would not ever
bring a קרבן korban for any of these cases of doubt. Ah,
okay. So you asked the רשב"א's Rashba question. The רשב"א Rashba has
a famous question and the רשב"א Rashba says we know that in
הלכה, halacha, if you have a case of doubt about something that
if you did it for sure you would bring a קרבן חטאת,
korban chatas, then in a case of doubt, you have to bring
a קרבן אשם, korban asham, אשם תלוי. asham talui. And therefore obviously
the תורה Torah cares, God cares, whether you've done something that was
a ספק. safek. And the רשב"א Rashba has a very long piece
in תורת הבית Toras HaBayis in the fourth בית bayis in the
first שער, shaar, and he at least to his satisfaction debunks what
he thinks the רמב"ם's Rambam approach is. But it's notable that the
רשב"א Rashba thinks that the רמב"ם's Rambam source is from our גמרא.
Gemara. And we're going to see, I think we already saw a
little bit and we'll see a little bit more today. So let's
take a look. And just to contrast one other piece of contrast,
which is that for the רמב"ם Rambam there's actually two different הלכות.
halachos. One is case of ספק, safek, that is the case itself
is in doubt. And there's a different הלכה halacha which the רמב"ם
Rambam quotes in הלכות ממרים Hilchos Mamrim about how the סנהדרין Sanhedrin
rules or how rabbis have to rule in specific cases at the
end of the first פרק perek the רמבם Rambam says: שני חכמים
או שני בתי דינין שנחלקו, shnei chachamim o shnei batei dinin she-necheleku,
if there's a dispute, two different rabbis... Disagree about something, or two
different courts disagree about something, בזמן שלא בזמן הסנהדרין *bizman shelo bizman
haSanhedrin*, if there's no centralized authority, that's how we've been living now
for 1700 years or so, או שלא היה הדבר ברור להם *o
shelo hayah hadavar barur lahem* or if the case has not yet
been fully decided to the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*. That is, either there's no
סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* at all, then there's no end to the מחלוקת machlokes.
*makhloket*, or even if there is a סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, but the סנהדרין
*Sanhedrin* hasn't decided it yet. בין בזמן אחד בין בזה אחר זה
*bein bizman ehad bein bezeh ahar zeh*, or even if they follow
each other in generations or hundreds of years later, אחד מטהר ואחד
מטמא אחד אוסר ואחד מתיר *ehad metaher ve-ehad metame ehad oser ve-ehad
mattir*. One is permissible and one is stringent. No matter what, אם
אין לך יודע להיכן הדין נוטה *im ein lekha yodea lehikan hadin
noreh*, if you, presumably anyone reading this or presumably any דיין *dayan*
who has to decide or any Rabbi who has to decide on
this case, if you cannot figure it out, you have both opinions
and you're not sure, בשל תורה Torah הלך אחר המחמיר *beshel Torah
halakh ahar hamahmir*, if it's a biblical law or a case that
applies to a biblical law, then you have to be stringent, you
have to follow the stringent opinion. בשל סופרים הלך אחר המקל *beshel
soferim halakh ahar hamekel*, and in the case of Rabbinic law, you
have to follow the lenient opinion. Now, what that means is on
a case-by-case basis or in resolving any specific dispute
post-סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*, there are no more rules about how to rule. The
rule is Rabbinic laws we'll be lenient as much as possible, and
biblical laws we should be stringent as much as possible. Again, this
רמב״ם *Rambam* is much debated and how to apply it, but those
two issues are often conflated: the question of ספק safek *safek* and
the question of מחלוקת machlokes *makhloket*. So it's important to note. Yeah.
There are things for which there's no מחמיר machmir *mahmir* or מקל
*mekel*, such as שיעורים *shiurim* will create a חומרא *humra* on one
end and a קולא *kula* on another end. You could be sure
that in almost any הלכתית שאילה *halakhik shayla*, in any specific case,
there may be what we would call מחמיר machmir *mahmir* and מקל
*mekel*, more strict or more lenient, but if the same ruling would
be applied to every case and would be relied upon across the
board, it would result in both קולות *kulot* and חומרות *humrot*. And
that's another important part of the הלכתית *halakhik* calculus is how to
figure out, are you really being lenient or are you really being
stringent? The case, the famous story of רב חיים בריסקר Rav Chaim
Brisker, *Rav Hayyim Brisker*, someone asked why is רב חיים Rav Chaim
בריסקר *Rav Hayyim Brisker* so מקל *mekel* on הלכות halachos שבת *Hilkhot
Shabbat*? And he says, I'm not מקל *mekel* on הלכות שבת *Hilkhot
Shabbat*, I'm מחמיר machmir *mahmir* on פיקוח נפש *pikuach nefesh*. That even
in the most what we would think insignificant cases of medical concern,
he tended to be permissive about calling a doctor or using different
kinds of, particularly Rabbinic things, and even biblical violations as well. Okay.
So we're on the second wide line on ע״ג ע״א *Ayin-Gimel Amud-Alef*.
אמר רבא amar Rava, *Amar Rava*, דבר תורה devar Torah שתוקי shtuki
כשר kasher, *devar Torah shtuki kasher*. So we saw already the משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* had mentioned someone called a שתוקי shtuki *shtuki*. שתוקי shtuki,
*Shtuki* is someone whose father we don't, is unidentified, but we know
who the mother is. So this is a child with one known
parent. The problem is if the father turns out to be someone
we didn't expect, he could end up marrying someone who he's not
allowed to marry and perhaps, perhaps there might not even, oh, no,
he's certainly Jewish if we know who the mother is, but he
might, he might be a ממזר mamzer *mamzer*, we don't know whether
he's a ממזר mamzer. *mamzer* or not, and he might be a
חלל *halal* or not, we don't know. I was thinking, I was
thinking. Okay, so right, שתוקי shtuki, *shtuki* first. So אמר רבא Amar
Rava דבר תורה שתוקי shtuki כשר kasher. *Amar Rava devar Torah shtuki
kasher*. So רבא Rava *Rava* says that fundamentally, a שתוקי shtuki? *shtuki*
at the תורה *Torah* level, at the biblical law level, שתוקי shtuki
*shtuki* would be okay. Now, how come שתוקי shtuki *shtuki*, why did
then the Rabbis have to come up with the rules of שתוקי
shtuki *shtuki*? We're going to have to see. So first, the suggestion
is that at the biblical level, שתוקי shtuki *shtuki* is okay. So
we're going to see why. מאי טעמא Mai ta’ama? *Mai ta'ama*, why?
רוב rov? כשרים אצלה *rov kesherim etzlah*, because this woman, we know
who the woman is, we know who the mother is, and most
of the men who could have been the father of this child
are כשרים לה *kesherim lah* in what sense? Either that they are
not her relatives, or if she is a regular Jewish woman, then
they are not ממזרים mamzerim, *mamzerim* or they are not נתינים *netinim*
or anything like that. And possibility number two is, what if the
men were non-Jewish? Well, then even if the men were non-Jewish, the
child will end up being a כשר kasher *kasher* Jew. There's
less than a רוב rov *rov*, I mean, there's more non-Jews than
Jews. Ah, but even if the husband, even if the father is
non-Jew, it's not a problem either. It's not כשר kasher *kasher* though.
No, the child would be כשר kasher *kasher*, yeah. We had that
a few דפים *dapim* ago. There's some positions that say, you know,
עובדי כוכבים *ovdei kokhavim*, הבא על בת ישראל Yisrael. הולד ממזר mamzer,
*haba al bat Yisrael havlad mamzer*. Okay, so at least, but we
don't פוסק posek *pasken* like that. We don't פוסק *pasken* that with
a non-Jewish father the child is a ממזר mamzer? *mamzer*, and therefore
רבא Rava *Rava* already knew that, that was a מחלוקת machlokes תנאים
*machloket tannaim* that was decided. So רבא Rava, *Rava* can say רוב
rov. כשרים אצלה *rov kesherim etzlah*. ומיעוט פסולים אצלה *umiyut pesulim etzlah*,
and it's only a minority who are going to be פסול pasul?
*pasul* to her. So ואי אזלי אינהו לגביה lgabei... *ve-ei azlei inhu
legabei*, and even if they would be coming to her, so that
means that the man comes to join with the woman. So כל
דפריש מרובא פריש kol d’parish m’ruba parish? *kol de-parish me-ruba parish*. We
can rely on the principle that whenever we take something out of
its normal place, we rely on the רוב rov *rov*. That is,
the man comes from his town and he goes to find a
woman in a different town, so he separated from the רוב rov,
*rov* of the people in his town. And since the רוב rov.
*rov* of there were כשרים *kesherim*, then we can assume that the
child would be כשר Kasher *kasher* as well. מה אמרת דילמא אזלה
איהי לגבייהו *mah amart dilma azlah ihi legabeihu*? What? Why do you
have to bring in כל דפריש מרובא פריש kol d’parish m’ruba parish
*kol de-parish me-ruba parish*? Isn't it like the whole idea of a
רוב rov, *rov*? So מימר דדילמא אזלא איהי לגביה הוא? But what
is the difference between כל דפריש kol d’parish and רוב דפריש? rov
d’parish? Isn’t that like the whole idea of a רוב? Very good
question. This is one of the central places again for talking about
רוב also ספק safek, and also רוב. And רוב again becomes a
huge topic about several different lines in חזל Chazal and אחרונים achronim
try to pick apart why what is there a difference between אזלינן
בתר רובא azlinan batar ruba and רובו ככולו rubo k’kulo and כל
דפריש מרובא פריש? kol d’parish m’ruba parish How do each of those
different principles about relying on a majority, how do those what are
the subtle differences between them, what kind of cases do they apply
to differently, why do חזל Chazal choose one over the other? So
here כל דפריש מרובא פריש kol d’parish m’ruba parish. is because talking
about the man left his his community or his town and he
went and met a woman from another town and they had a
child. So that’s he was extracted from his locale so we’re going
to see it’s contrasted to קבוע kavuah because if she left her
town and went to him, מיזל אזלא איהי לגביה הוה ליה קבוע.
meizal azla eehi lgabei havah lei kavuah. See, he left לגביה... he
left... same town? Okay. Okay נו, nu, I don’t know because you
don’t want to have this extra marital or non I guess non-marital
relationship with someone who’s in the same town. I don’t know. Maybe
someone left the street and came into her house let’s say.
Even there, right. So that even if the man is just coming
into her home, that’s already כל דפריש מרובא פריש kol d’parish m’ruba
parish. coming into her home. But if she left and went to
him, then that’s קבוע kavuah meaning that the man the man remains
stationary to the extent either in the same city or in the
same house. So the גמרא Gemara has two possibilities: either she went
to him or he went to her. Is a third possibility they
went to a motel, a third location? So in that case that’s
also כל דפריש מרובא פריש. kol deparish meruba parish, Both of them
left from their... We’re on the third wide line on עג עמוד
א. Ayin Gimmel Amud Aleph. Okay. So כל דפריש מרובא פריש. מאי
אמר דילמא אזלא איהי לגביה הוה ליה קבוע? mai amar dilma azla
eehi lgabei havah lei kavuah? Maybe she went to go be with
him? So הוה ליה קבוע. havah lei kavuah. So then the man
will be fixed and we have a different principle: כל קבוע כמחצה
על מחצה דמי. kol kavuah k’mechetza al mechetza dami. When we have
something that is stationary, a fixed איסור, issur, we consider that to
be 50/50 ספק, safek. not a majority minority kind of ספק. safek,
So in the case of when the woman was stationary and the
man was being פורש poresh from the רוב, so then we could
rely on the רוב. But if the woman goes to the man
then it’s considered קבוע kavuah and the concern will be at least
a higher level concern. But nonetheless, התורה אמרה לא יבא ממזר ממזר
ודאי הוא דלא יבא. haTorah amrah lo yavo mamzer mamzer vadai hu
d’lo yavo. We know the Torah has a specific exclusion of ספק
ממזר. safek mamzer. That is the only ממזר mamzer? who’s prohibited from
coming into the Jewish people is the ממזר ודאי, mamzer vadai, a
certain ממזר. mamzer But if there’s any kind of ספק, safek if
there’s any kind of doubt about the whether or not he is
a ממזר, mamzer then that’s allowed. הא ממזר ספק יבא בקהל. ha
mamzer safek yavo b’kahal. And a ספק ממזר safek mamzer is allowed
to come in. So according to the רשבא Rashba that’s the proof
for the רמבם. Rambam. The רשבא Rashba thinks that the רמבם’s Rambam
proof that in general the rule of ספק דאורייתא לחומרא safek d’Oraita
l’chumra is itself only a rabbinic law is because at the biblical
level ספק ממזר safek mamzer is kosher and therefore ספק safek anything
is kosher according to the רמבם. Rambam. And the רשבא Rashba disagrees,
the רשבא Rashba thinks ספק ממזר safek mamzer is a special exception
to the Torah’s general rule that ספק safek, you have to treat
stringently. So there’s two different ways to read how this גמרא Gemara
works. Is this a model for every other case in the Torah
or is this an exception? Okay. So והתורה אמרה לא יבא ממזר
ממזר ודאי הוא דלא יבא הא ממזר ספק יבא בקהל. v’haTorah amrah
lo yavo mamzer mamzer vadai hu d’lo yavo ha mamzer safek yavo
b’kahal. So a ספק ממזר safek mamzer could come into the Jewish
people, he could marry into the Jewish people. So בקהל ודאי הוא
דלא יבא. b’kahal vadai hu d’lo yavo. He’s also not allowed to
marry into only a ודאי קהל, vadai kahal, that is that the
Jewish people, their level of כשרות kashrut is at a level of
ודאי, vadai, דלא יבא הא בקהל ספק יבא. d’lo yavo ha b’kahal
safek yavo. So even a ודאי ממזר vadai mamzer could marry into
a Jewish community of a Jewish person whose כשרות kashrut was בספק
b’safek as well. So a ספק ממזר safek mamzer could marry a
perfectly good kosher Jew and a ודאי ממזר vadai mamzer could marry
a Jewish person whose כשרות kashrut is בספק. b’safek. Those two possibilities
from this דרשה drasha at the biblical level. In the רשבא’s Rashba
view, is the רמבם Rambam saying that whatever the Torah says, whatever
לאו lav it’s אסור, assur, it’s whatever it says you know only
definite things and not like we’re not deriving this from deriving everything
else from ממזר? mamzer Right, something like that. And to a certain
extent both positions are based on סברא. sevara. Actually there is one
one exception. There’s a פסוק pasuk in the end of פרשת שופטים
Parshat Shoftim I think it is talking about when you go in
a siege and talking about building a siege engine and which kind
of trees can you cut down. And it says עץ אשר ידעת
כי לא עץ מאכל הוא. etz asher yadata ki lo etz ma’achal
hu. Only if you know for sure that it is not a
fruit-bearing tree then you could cut it down. And some אחרונים achronim
use that as a biblical proof for the רשבא’s Rashba position that
at a דאורייתא d’Oraita level you have to be sure that it’s
not a fruit-bearing tree. So even a ספק איסור safek issur of
cutting down a fruit tree, the Torah says explicitly would be prohibited.
So that’s another possibility in the פסוקים psukim for support for the
רשבא’s Rashba position and to extensive debate in the אחרונים. acharonim. Okay.
ממזר ועבד לא ספק יבוא ומה טעמם דשתוקי פסול. mamzer ve'eved lo
safek yavo umah ta'amam deshtuki pasul. So then if the whole point,
רבא Rava just told us that a שתוקי shtuki is כשר, Kasher
that is at the דאורייתא de'oraita level, שתוקי shtuki, could marry whomever
he wants because at the worst he is a ספק ממזר, safek
mamzer, and ספק ממזר safek mamzer is allowed to marry the Jewish
people. So why did they say שתוקי פסול? גזירה שמא ישא אחותו
מאביו. shtuki pasul gezeira shema yisa achoto me'aviv. Maybe since we don't
know who the father is, maybe the woman he'll end up wanting
to marry, her father will have been his father. And therefore he'll
end up marrying... he can't marry anyone. Oh, so that's exactly the
concern. So the concern is that therefore he should only marry whom
he is allowed to marry? ממזרים, גרים, gerim, other שתוקי, shtuki things
like that, people whose כשרות kashrus is much lower. So we're going
to see. So what? So this is a first suggestion. It's going
to be rejected. We say, possibility number one, שתוקי פסול shtuki pasul?
גזירה שמא ישא אחותו מאביו. gezeira shema yisa achoto me'aviv. Maybe he'll
marry his paternal sister. אלא מעתה שתוקי שתוקית לא ישא שמא ישא
אחותו מאביו. ela me'ata shtuki shtukit lo yisa shema yisa achoto me'aviv.
So couldn't you say, well then he should not be allowed to
marry anyone, even another שתוקי, that is a male שתוקי can't marry
a female שתוקי? Maybe they have the same father even if they
have two different mothers. Okay. כל כי הני מזנו ואזלי? kol ki
hani mezaneu ve'azlei? Does the same man go out with all the
different women in the town and all of the שתוקים? shtukis? So
it's a certain... the גמרא Gemara says that that's an absurd conclusion.
Which is that... It's more likely. The suggestion... the גמרא Gemara rejects
the notion that every שתוקי in town are all the children of
the same man, and therefore no matter what, still even to marry
a שתוקי would be, would be itself כל דפריש מרובא פריש, the
risk of marrying his sister is very low.
Okay. Charlie, you have a question? Yeah, this is the Babylonian תלמוד
Talmud in... had this been part of ירושלמי Yerushalmi they might not
have been so surprised at that, because the level of licentiousness was
unbelievable. Well, in בבל Bavel it was certainly a concern as well.
I don't know enough to... from the גמרא Gemara's perspective on that
to comment further, but it's certainly an interesting question. Why can't he
marry... why can't he marry a גיורת giyoret or something like that?
So, okay, but that's exactly the same kind of אלא מעתה. ela
me'ata. That is a case where we're quite sure, or even a
hundred percent sure, that there is no concern that this woman's father
is his father, then what's the problem? So בת שתוקית לא ישא
שמא ישא אחותו מאביו. bat shtukit lo yisa shema yisa achoto me'aviv.
Couldn't you also say he should not be allowed to marry בת
שתוקית, bat shtukit, that is even the daughter of a woman who
was a שתוקי and even several steps down? Because no matter what,
he could end up being related to this woman's father no matter
what. Even if he knows who the father is, he's not going
to know that that's not his father because he doesn't know who
his father is. אלא לא שכיחא. ela lash'chi'cha. So that case is
totally implausible, totally rare. הכא נמי לא שכיחא. hacha nami lo sh'chi'cha.
And this case of בת שתוקית bat shtukit is also very rare,
it's impossible, you would never find such a case, the risk is
very low. אלא מעלה עשו ביוחסין. ela ma'alasu beyuchsin. No, no, no.
There's not really any good reason to say that שתוקי is אסור.
assur. שתוקי is a גזירה דרבנן. gezeira derabbanan. The rabbis made a
higher standard and a lower standard for יוחסין. yuchsin. This part of
the main... the theme of this פרק, perek, which is that yeah,
some of these laws are not necessarily a hundred percent logical, but
they follow because the rabbis decided that there should be that gradation
and many different tiers. The מהרש"א, Maharsha, right at the beginning of
the פרק perek says the ten different levels of ייחוס yichus are
comparable to the ten different levels of קדושה kedusha in ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. Going in the first פרק perek of כלים, Keilim, it
talks about how the Land of Israel has a higher קדושה kedusha
than other lands, and Jerusalem and the walled cities are better than
other kinds of cities, and Jerusalem is better than other walled cities,
and the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash and going closer and closer. So
those ten levels of קדושה kedusha are comparable to the ten layers
of ייחוס yichus that the rabbis instituted those kinds of boundaries and
protections just as a way of heightening the understanding of people's כשרות,
kashrus, people's...
you know, trying to maintain their familial status. Interestingly enough, the רמב"ם,
Rambam, if you look, take a look at the last page of
the רמב"ם Rambam's פירוש המשנה, Perush HaMishnah, and the רמב"ם Rambam mentions
somewhere else in a תשובה, teshuvah, I think, also he's talking about
ייחוס, yichus, and he says even the most base Jewish families keep
a record of their ancestry going back ten generations. And the רמב"ם
Rambam lists his family back many generations, you know, he's משה בן
מימון Moshe ben Maimon and מימון Maimon is the son of so-and-so,
and going back many, many steps through great דיינים Dayanim and rabbis
who were in Spain at the time, and he tells you what
they did, they were הדיין, hadayan, they were הרב harav this. So
it really is to show that families should take a care to
really, you know, be proud of their ancestry. You know, many of
us, even if our ancestors weren't great rabbis, but they did wonderful
things and because of them that we're here. So we should really
have a lot of gratitude for that. So אמר רבא, Rava דאורייתא
אסופי כשר. de'oraita asufi kasher. So now
we just had the same סוגיא sugya about שתוקי, so now he's
going to say about אסופי asufi as well. Now אסופי, asufi, yes.
Just...
I thought yesterday Rabbi Linzer was going in a direction of leniency
in general. So is this like a pushback in a way, right?
To say מעלה עשו ביוחסין, ma’ale asu biyuchsin, that is, we have
a higher standard, right? We have a higher standard but we are
acknowledging that it is a rabbinic law. So that means there is
still some amount of flexibility about some of these things and there
are wiggle room and ways to get out of them and all
sorts of, you know, with rabbinic laws already, there’s a lot of
places you can build in. Like we said already, the whole notion
of ספק, safek as soon as you have a ספק safek about
a rabbinic law, then you’re home free. So I was just wondering
about like a בעל תשובה ba’al teshuvah in modern in contemporary... Yeah,
exactly. בעל תשובה Ba’al teshuvah marrying into a family that’s very concerned
about this. Where would that family probably focus their bottom line? On
this idea or on the idea that, well, maybe that person really
even though we don’t know his parentage, you know, is... Right. I
would think even most בעלי תשובה ba’alei teshuvah nowadays come from families
who we at least know who the parents are. They’re not total
orphans and things like that. Right. And they have a... Right, so
the concern is not as high as something like שתוקי or אסופי.
asufi. It’s just a person who may not be from a quote-unquote
good family or who knows. רב משה Rav Moshe does have an
interesting תשובה teshuvah where he talks about there’s a ברייתא braita that’s
not so well-known for good reasons not so well-known, that there are
all these terrible things about someone who is a בן נידה, ben
niddah, that is a child who was born to a woman who
was in a state of נידה niddah at the time
when the baby was conceived. And רב משה Rav Moshe totally, because
what happened was this family wanted to marry this young man and
he was a בעל תשובה ba’al teshuvah and he came from this
family and his mother hadn’t been observing הלכות נידה. hilchot niddah. But
he was a really great guy and he was gonna be a
really great match for their daughter and they really wanted, but we
read this ברייתא braita that says it’s a bad thing. And so
רב משה Rav Moshe basically demolishes the whole idea and says, look,
in the end if he’s a good guy, he’s a good match
for your daughter and you think that he’s the right and they’re
happy together, and the גמרא Gemara talks about all the terrible qualities
of a person who is a בן נידה, ben niddah, therefore since
he’s such a good guy, he must not be a בן נידה.
ben niddah. So he basically demolishes the whole category. And there’s lots
to be said about that which is that, what? Rabbi Linzer says
this. Yeah, so that’s רב משה's Rav Moshe תשובה teshuvah which deals
exactly with this question, that is, when a drop in the ocean...
Right, so there are places that people get caught up on ייחוס,
yichus, but in most cases there’s really not anything הלכתי halachic to
be worried about. Some cases there are, but usually not so much.
Okay, so רבא Rava says, דבר תורה אסופי כשר. asufi kasher. So
it’s gonna be a similar line of argumentation. מאי טעמא? mai ta’ama?
אשת איש Eshet ish בבעלה תליא. bi’ba’ala talya. So what is it
again? אסופי Asufi is someone totally an orphan, unknown parentage
entirely. אסוף מן השוק. Asuf min hashuk. They just, you know, found
him on the street. And we’re gonna find out exactly where do
you find such a baby in the street such that he counts
as an אסופי asufi or not. So this אסופי asufi at least
at the biblical level could be כשר. So מאי טעמא? אשת איש
Eshet ish בבעלה תליא. bi’ba’ala talya. If there’s a woman who had
to give up her baby because and she was married, so then
of course the baby’s father is most likely or even a hundred
percent likely to be the father, the husband. That is, her husband
is almost entirely likely to be the father of the child, and
therefore even any married woman who’s giving up a child, presumably the
baby is a כשר anyway. So we don’t have to worry about
אסופי. asufi. Okay. So מאי איכא? Mai ika?
מיעוט
ארוסות Mi’ut arusot ומיעוט שהלך בעליהן למדינת הים. umi’ut shehalach ba’aleihen limdinat
hayam. What about the two other possibilities, that is ארוסות, arusot, that
is women who were married to their husbands but had not yet
consummated the marriage, and therefore the father is some other man and
she had been involved extramaritally with another man while she was מקודשת
mekudeshet and now the baby would be a ממזר? mamzer Or even
נשואות nesuot women, women who had consummated their marriages but then their
husbands went away to India for a long business trip of several
years and in the meantime she got pregnant and had to give
up the baby, and that’s therefore the baby would be a ממזר
mamzer because she was a married woman? So כיון דאיכא פנויה ואיכא
נמי דמחמת רעבון, keivan de’ika pnuyah ve’ika nami demachmat ra’avon, הוי פלגא
ופלגא. hava palga upalga. So because there are two other cases which
it could be, that is פנויה, pnuyah, a totally unmarried woman, and
therefore her child would not be a ממזר mamzer even with whatever
man. Or a woman, that is a married woman, even from a
נשואין nisuin who had to give up her baby because of רעבון
ra’avon during a period of famine, that is she couldn’t feel that
she could provide for this baby and this is their best attempt
at trying to give the baby up to adoption, obviously putting a
baby in the street is closer to murder than it would be
giving the baby to an adoption agency. Basket in the Nile... Basket
in the Nile, so it’s not murder obviously, but providing, not being
able to provide for a newborn baby, the baby most likely will
die unless someone takes care of it. But the גמרא Gemara says
הוי פלגא ופלגא. hava palga upalga. That’s like fifty-fifty. Only when they
stayed in baskets on the doorstep of the orphanage... On the door
of the orphanage or on the door of רב חיים's, Rav Chaim
רב חיים's Rav Chaim house. Is this?
רב חיים Rav Chaim בריסקר, another רב חיים Rav Chaim story. So
supposedly רב חיים Rav Chaim was the address for אסופים. asufim. Well
not really אסופים, asufim, we’ll see, but when when people would have
children that they couldn’t support, they had too many children or they
were too poor or anything like that or they were the wrong
age or the wrong family or anything like that, רב Rav חיים
supposedly would wake up several times throughout the night every night just
to check his front step because if there was a baby he
had to take them in. to take care of it. So רב
Rav חיים was a great
Talmudist and רב of the town, but he was also the orphanage.
So it's important to think about what does it mean to be
the רב of a town.
I'm sure he provided for them, I don't think he just raised
them in his own home. He would probably help to coordinate people
who could adopt the children, but it's just important that his address,
his house, was the address. You needed a place to drop off
a baby, that was at the rabbi's house.
Something like that. So there you go.
So פלגא ופלגא, palga u'palga, so the גמרא Gemara considers that to
be fifty-fifty. התורה אמרה לא יבא ממזר בקהל ה'. HaTorah amra lo
yavo mamzer b'kahal Hashem. א ממזר A mamzer can't marry into קהל
ה'. kahal Hashem. But ממזר ודאי הוא דלא יבא, הא ממזר ספק
יבא. mamzer vadai hu d'lo yavo, ha mamzer safek yavo. בקהל ודאי
הוא דלא יבא, הא בקהל ספק יבא. B'kahal vadai hu d'lo yavo,
ha b'kahal safek yavo. This is the same argument we saw before,
that is a ספק ממזר safek mamzer could even marry a kosher
Jew and a ממזר Mamzer could marry into a ספק ספק safek
safek kosher Jew. And therefore, in such a case already, since it's
fifty-fifty, it's פלגא ופלגא, palga u'palga, because we had two cases on
each side now. Obviously, I don't know the incidence rates of each
of them, but the גמרא Gemara calls it fifty-fifty. It's enough to
say there's a ספק safek, either way.
So therefore, we could say, oh, so this is a worst-case scenario.
The אסופי asufi is a ספק ממזר safek mamzer and therefore ספק
ממזר safek mamzer should still be able to marry a Jewish woman
or an אסופית asufit should be able to marry a Jewish man.
So what's the problem? Wait, I just want to get that actually
straight. Sure. If they were תולה בבעלה, tola b'baalah, would it not
be תולה בבעלה tola b'baalah anything? Wouldn't it be more to advantage
to be תולה בבעלה? tola b'baalah? I mean, but she can't be
תולה בבעלה tola b'baalah because they haven't... "we were in love, we
couldn't contain ourselves." Our understanding of the times, especially in בבל, Bavel,
was that they were not together, meaning they did the אירוסין, eirusin,
he would move to some other town and he would be working
there and she would be living here in her parents' house. יהודה
Yehuda is different. We know the משנה Mishnah. in כתובות Ketubot says
that in ארץ יהודה, Eretz Yehuda, at least during the Tannaitic period
or during זמן המקדש, zman haMikdash, the men and women after אירוסין
eirusin would have ייחוד yichud together to kind of get to know
each other better before they would be married and something like that.
So there at least there's a lower ability to claim that they
had not been sexually intimate at that point because already they had
had ייחוד yichud together. But certainly in בבל Bavel and even in
other parts of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael at the time, that practice
was not tolerated. Okay. So the same argument, that is ספק ממזר
safek mamzer should be okay. מאי טעמא אמרו אסופי פסול? Mai taama
amru asufi pasul? So why'd they say אסופי asufi is פסול? Pasul.
שמא ישא אחותו מאביו, Shema yisa achoto me'aviv, maybe he'll marry his
sister. אלא מעתה אסופי אסופית לא ישא? Ela maata asufi asufit lo
yisa? So and then you should say, well, if you're going to
say that he's not allowed to marry a kosher Jew because maybe
she's his sister, so then he shouldn't even be able to marry
another אסופית asufit because maybe she's also his sister. או דילמא שמא
ישא אחותו מאביו בין מאמו O dilma shema yisa achoto me'aviv bein
me'imo or even his maternal sister even, which, you know, both a
maternal sister and a paternal sister are prohibited as עריות. arayot. וכי
הני שדי ואזלי? V'chi hanei shadei v'azlei? You're going to tell me
that all of those אסופים asufim in the same town are from
the same woman and the same man? Again, the same argument, that
is how can every abandoned child in town be from the same
family? Okay. באסופי לא ישא שמא ישא אחותו? B'asufi lo yisa shema
yisa achoto? No, or you'll make the same argument. If you're going
to tell me that he's not allowed to marry a kosher Jew,
then he also shouldn't be able to marry even the descendants one
step down because it could also be the same kind of עריות.
arayot. You know, such a person could end up being his father
anyway, so therefore it would be his sister. אלא לא שכיח הכא
נמי לא שכיח. Ela lo shechiach hacha nami lo shechiach. So such
a case is totally far-fetched and rare, and therefore such a case
is also totally far-fetched and rare. We don't have to worry about
it. אלא מעתה אלא מעלה עשו ביוחסין. Ela maata ela maala asu
b'yuchsin. And so too even אסופי, asufi, that is a person who
has no known parentage at all, nonetheless at the דאורייתא d'Oraita level
would be totally כשר because of we have רוב, we have ספק,
safek we have all of these halachic principles to rely on that
would provide כשרות kashrut for such a person. Nonetheless, the Rabbis held
it back a little bit to say look if you don't know
who your parents are you shouldn't marry a kosher Jew,
which is an interesting point just to say מעלה עשו ביוחסין. maala
asu b'yuchsin. They made these gradations within יחוס yichus stricter than what
the תורה would demand. So to sperm donors for a minute. Ah,
so sperm... okay, but you know what I'm going to ask. No,
no, no, it's a good question. Ask the question. So basically I
thought like, you know, from what I heard, right, that like, you
know, if a woman is going to do that, that you make
sure it's not going to be a Jewish sperm donor because of
blah blah blah. So like, you know, if all this is such
a rare, you know, then is it the same idea that מעלה
עשו ביוחסין maala asu b'yuchsin sort of or like... so this is
a question about about artificial insemination and sperm donation and things like
that which in many cases have been an incredible resource for people
with fertility challenges and so it's important to note רב משה פיינשטיין
Rav Moshe Feinstein already I think in the sixties has a תשובה
tshuva and it's in
the
first חלק chelek in אגרות משה Igrot Moshe and רב משה Rav
Moshe rules leniently. conception and things like that because that’s not a
sexual act. A ממזר Mamzer has to be created not just from
the genetic material of two people who are not allowed to marry
each other or through a physical action of
implanting whatever type of material, but that it has to be actually
through a sexual act. And the Satmar Rav supposedly, the Satmar Rav
ruled against Rav Moshe. The Satmar Rav very much opposed artificial insemination,
fierce מחלוקת. Actually I was talking with Rabbi yesterday about this. There’s
a story at least that there was some Satmar חסידים Chassidim who
were involved in burning some of Rav Moshe's books because of that.
So really it was a fierce debate about obviously קדושת ישראל kedushas
Yisroel and important questions of יחוס, yichus, but also about how to
provide
support for people with infertility. And I think nowadays almost every פוסק
in the world, as far as I know, maybe I don’t know
about Satmar, but you know,
mainstream פוסקים, poskim, I guess you would say, even in the חרדי
Chareidi ישיבה yeshiva world, certainly would rely on Rav Moshe's position just
because it doesn’t make any sense otherwise. Because to be a ממזר
Mamzer, you have to have done something wrong. The parents have to
have done something wrong, but to say that a physical medical procedure,
or even not so medical, but just that it’s not a sexual
procedure, it’s not an act of sex, how could that create ממזרות?
mamzerus? And that’s really Rav Moshe's argument. He goes through and he
brings גמרות Gemoras for it as well, which is very interesting. Some
strange גמרות Gemoras that until now didn’t make any sense. People who
got pregnant from going to the bath and things like that, and
it’s like how can you talk about that? But that’s the suggestion
that somehow that was the גמרא's Gemara way of talking about a
case where a woman could have become pregnant from coming in contact
with semen even if it were not through a sexual encounter.
Similar but not exactly identical issue is an ovum donation. Right, and
again some of these questions get dealt with extensively about even so
when we know who the sperm donor is, we know who the
egg donor is, there are all sorts of things like that, and
then how do you determine the יחוס? yichus? Does it only go
by the birth mother? Does it count as someone who has no
הלכה halacha father? Can you count the sperm donor as a הלכה
halacha father or not? And that becomes a question about, not about
ממזרות, mamzerus, but about
עריות arayos for such a child to be aware of people he
should or shouldn’t marry. And then if it was a non-Jewish sperm
donor it would be better and things like that. And then the
question of egg donation. What if it’s a Jewish sperm donor? What
are the... Well that’s exactly the question, the question of מיהות? mihus?
And this is actually this question, so the פוסקים poskim deal with
that, I’ll say in short, it gets addressed and some people are
מחמיר machmir and some people are מיקל. meikel. Okay, תא שמע. ta
shema. אמר רב אבא בר הונא: Amar Rav Abba bar Huna:
מצאו מהול, matzu mahul, what if they found this אסופי asupi baby
is found to have been
circumcised? אין בו משום אסופי. ein bo mishum asupi. Then such a
baby is not considered an אסופי. asupi. That is someone whose parents
we don’t know who he is, we have no idea, there’s a
baby sitting here, unknown baby, but he’s already been circumcised.
Not an אסופי. asupi. אסופי asupi means dropped him off before the
מילה. mila. Wait is this in an era that non-Jews were not
getting circumcised? You’d say the same thing. Certainly. That’s an interesting question
as well. But people get circumcised or not? Okay so that’s an
interesting question, but here this is even saying even a Jewish person
who’s had a מילה, mila, the presumption is that the הלכה halachic
category of אסופי, asupi, that is we’re concerned there is even the
slight ספק safek that he’s a ממזר Mamzer or that he shouldn’t
marry into a Jewish girl, in such a case we would say,
look, such a person who’s had a מילה, mila, the parents were
good parents who had to drop him
off, not that they were
people who shouldn’t have married each other. That is, the fact that
they kept the baby around for a week and did the מילה
mila and hired the מוהל, mohel, that’s enough to say that he’s
not an אסופי. asupi. Okay, does that still stand today? I heard...
I would think so, it’s an open and closed גמרא, Gemara, I
would think that’s the rule. The question is whether it’s relying on
the fact that the non-Jews there didn’t have circumcisions or not, I
don’t know. Here it sounds like it’s just saying that the parents
had enough care to provide the מילה mila for him, that means
that they are כשר parents. You’re saying nowadays if a baby shows
up on your doorstep you don’t even know whether it’s a Jewish
baby or not. That’s even a separate question which the גמרא Gemara
even doesn’t deal with. And I’m saying the presence of a מילה
mila doesn’t prove anything because non-Jews also do מילה, mila, more as
you know. Yeah for sure. Okay we’ll keep going. So משופיהו, meshofeyhu,
so what if they had straightened out his limbs? This is something
I guess you have to do with newborn babies, I’m not a
hundred percent sure or nowadays we don’t do that but back then
they did. They had to kind of if they were bow-legged or
something like that, they would
strap them to some kind of frame or something to straighten out
their limbs. רש"י Rashi says איבריו מתוקנים ומיושרים, eivarav mesukanim umeyusharim, he’s
straightened out the legs. He says even in the early 20th century.
Okay so they were doing it in the early 20th century, so
we don’t do it nowadays as far as I know, maybe they
do. Okay, אין בו משום אסופי. ein bo mishum asupi. So too
it means that the parents... So too, it means that the parents
took some care to ensure that this baby grows up properly and
is healthy. So the fact that the baby was found in the
street is not enough of a reason to say that his יחוס
Yichus is in
doubt. So he's not an אסופי. Asufi. אסופי Asufi means totally abandoned,
totally neglected. And here, and therefore this is a baby who—it's—we don't
know who'd be the means halachically? Halachically an אסופי Asufi cannot marry
a ישראל. Right, and therefore if the
kid loses train—he's—it works—we're being מיקל. Meikel. No, he's less פסול. No,
he's—we assume that the parents took care of him and then he
fell out of the back of the trunk or something. You know,
like and therefore they were Jewish? I don't understand. That we assume
that if it's a כשר baby with Jewish parents and then he
was perfectly fine. This just seems like it's mixing
the—you could say ספק דרבנן לקולא. Safek d'rabanan l'kula. You could say
that. As soon as—as soon as it was shown that the parents
were taking care of him, we immediately can just say, okay, נו,
Nu, fine. This kind of addresses the יחוס Yichus thing from, it
seems to me, from a behavioral, you know, and a sociological standpoint.
Like okay, if somebody was looked after as a child, he probably
comes from a good family, right? Not a
הלכה Halacha כשר family, a good—some ממזר Mamzer. parents—but that means right,
well that's because from a sociological point of view, they're embarrassed about
it, right, they want to cover it up. But so the ראשונים
Rishonim here already pick up on this concern and say about מילה
Milah in particular, look, so that's kind of a question about how
much would parents of a ממזר Mamzer. be willing to really do
everything they need to do to ensure that the child grows up
properly and has a מילה Milah and grows up healthy and things
like that. It sounds like at least the stigma, הלכה Halacha it's
inexcusable, but the stigma was that if you have a ממזר, the
ממזר you don't want to have to deal with a ממזר. You
want to give up the ממזר. You want to neglect this child.
And so that's at least part of the—underlying some of this. Part
of the mindset. Part of the mindset that if he's from a
family, you know, you're not just— Okay, so משוח ומהול וכחול, Mashuach
u'mahul v'kachul, so if he's been anointed with oil, or if he
had eye shadow put on, those are things I guess they used
to do to
babies. So רמי חמרא תלי פתקא. Rami chamra tali pitka. And if
he was—now okay, so what is it?
רמי—sorry,
I lost my רש״י, Rashi it should have been in the...
Okay, רמי חמרא, Rami chamra, so either he was tied up with
the kinds of medicinal things, he had a necklace that had some
kind of charms on it or something, or פתקא, Pitka, he had
an amulet of some kind, or תלי קמיעא, Tali kemeia, or he
had some other kind of amulet, so אין בו משום אסופי. Ein
bo mishum asufi. So because again, the parents are taking care of
him. So I don't know, does this count as making sure, you
know, if you find a kid who has his vaccination slip on
his jumper, that means he's also not an אסופי. Asufi. Something like
that. Like the parents are taking care of the child. The baby
has had medicine, the baby has been taken care of, the baby
has been provided for. Okay. תלי בדיקלי, Tali b'diklei, what if he's
hanging from a palm tree in a basket presumably or swaddled up?
Yeah, something like that, rock-a-bye baby. Okay. אי מטיא ליה חיה, Ei
matya leh chaya, יש בו משום אסופי. yesh bo mishum asufi. If
it is a place where an animal could get to him, so
he is an אסופי, Asufi, because the parents put him there in
order that he should get eaten by wild
animals. ואם לאו, V'im lav, אין בו משום אסופי. ein bo mishum
asufi. And
if
it was a place in the tree where an animal couldn't get
to him, you know, the raccoons aren't going to bother the baby,
so then he's not an אסופי Asufi because the parents put him
there to protect him, even if it was a place, you know,
maybe I'll come back tomorrow or something, I don't know. But something
like that. Okay. סרדיתא סמיכה למתא, Sardita semicha l'mata, יש בו משום
אסופי. yesh bo mishum asufi. So if it was in a case
where, now this is in some kind of a ditch, right? Oh,
he was hanging on a tree that's called סרדיתא, Sardita, a different
kind of tree.
Okay. רש״י says called selerier. So I'm not sure what kind of
tree that is. Sorb translated as sorb tree. Sorb tree. Oh, okay.
Whatever that is. I don't know what kind of tree that is.
Okay. Okay, so יש בו משום אסופי Yesh bo mishum asufi ואם
לאו, v'im lav, אין בו משום אסופי. ein bo mishum asufi. It's
something similar to the palm tree argument which is that if it's
in the right kind of a place in the tree that the
baby would be safe, then it's—it's the opposite. What? Why? Because the
tree is... because it's a spiky tree. Or whatever. Or שדין Shedin
attack the trees. Okay, oh those kind of sorb trees distance from
a city do not harbor— Okay, so that's why, because nearby demons
like to hang out near the city and therefore the demons would
be bothering the baby, but if it was in a tree that
was far away from the city then it would be okay. Okay,
סמיכה למתא, Semicha l'mata, that's the real question. ואיכא דאמרי משיצי שדי.
V'ika d'amri meshizei shedi. Right, the trees have the demons in them.
Okay. Okay, I'm not an expert on demons, so I don't know.
Okay. Okay. רבא אמר משום דנפישי. Rava amar mishum de'nefishi.
Okay. So בי כנישתא bei knishta סמיכה למתא, smicha lemata, what if
he was found in the שול shul close to the city, ושכיחי
בה רבים, ve'shichichi bei rabim, and there are a lot of people
there, אין בו משום אסופי. ein bo mishum asufi. You drop him
off at שול, shul, it's interesting to note also the שול shul
is outside of the city. That's an interesting Babylonian... it was
because of the Persian rule, they had to build the שולס shuls
outside of the city or perhaps they specifically did it so that
for people going to work, it would be more convenient. The שול
shul would be out in the fields, so you could go דאבן
daven and then you would come home afterwards. And there are a
number of practices in our דאבנינג davening based on the Babylonian practice
that are because the שול shul was outside of town. If you
remember also at the end of the first פרק, perek, I forget
now which of the אמוראים Amora'im it was, but one of them
had to sleep overnight in the שול shul and killed the demon
during when he was דאבנינג davening מעריב. Ma'ariv. So also, there would
be demons in the שולס shuls because the שול shul was outside
of town. Okay.
So אין בו משום אסופי. ein bo mishum asufi. ואי לא, ve'i
lo, יש בו משום אסופי. yesh bo mishum asufi. And if you
drop him off at שול shul but it was not so close
to the town and there weren't a lot of people going to
that שול, shul, then it would be an אסופי. asufi. אמר אמימר,
Amar Ameimar, so האי פירא דסופלא יש בו משום אסופי. hai pira
de'sufla yesh bo mishum asufi. So if it was in a... what
is this? פירא דסופלא pira de'sufla נמצא בחריצתא? nimtza be'charitzata? Yeah. One
against each other, right? Let's say you found a baby who's whole
body's in the שול... shul...
I think our point, the thrust of this סוגיא sugya is to
say as much as we want to say that the baby is
not an אסופי, asufi, whenever case, whatever case we can to say
the baby's not an אסופי, asufi, we say he's not an אסופי.
asufi. That is, you have to be the most neglected, most left
behind, right? It's a backing off from the משנה. Mishnah The משנה
mishna sounds like it means אסופי asufi means someone we don't know
who the parents are. That's מעלה ביוחסין. ma'ala be'yuchsin. But now we're
backing it off and saying no, no, no, it's someone who we
don't know who their parents are who was neglected, who was left
out in the abandoned שול shul far away from town and didn't
have a מילה milah and didn't have oil and didn't have his
limbs straightened out. All those other criteria make it much harder to
classify someone as an אסופי. asufi. So the category still exists, but
it basically you end up saying ספק אסופי safek asufi is fine
and any kind of ספק safek. we can introduce into whether this
kid is an אסופי asufi or not, we leave it behind. So
that's a really important principle here that חז"ל, Chazal, that is the
אמוראים Amora'im already are pointing us away from categorizing people as אסופי.
asufi.
Interesting to consider, maybe there was מעלה ביוחסין, ma'ala be'yuchsin, they made
a higher level יוחסין yuchsin and then they backed it off in
some sense. That is, maybe it wasn't sustainable, maybe it was people
were saying maybe Babylonia had different levels of these kind of children
being born, a lot of possibilities. Okay. So האי פירא דסופלא יש
בו משום אסופי. hai pira de'sufla yesh bo mishum asufi. That's a
ditch where they would store the תמרי, tmari, the dates, when they
were harvested. רש"י Rashi says they would or they would put the
pits of the dates for the animals to eat, because I guess
the pits of the dates still have some of the sugar on
it. So you could imagine cows want to or goats would want
to go and lick the sugar off of the date pits. So
חיצרא דנהרא, chitzra de'nahara, or on the bank of the river, אין
בו משום אסופי. ein bo mishum asufi. Also פשרי, pashrei, but in
a different part of the bank of the river that is a
place where there are fewer people, יש בו משום אסופי. yesh bo
mishum asufi. In that place because again, if you put the baby
down by the docks, maybe it's because you want someone to find
the baby. So that's not an אסופי. asufi. But you put the
baby down totally far down river from town and no one's gonna
find the baby and then someone does find the baby, that's a
little bit different. It's interesting to think about משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu.
משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu really was someone who was totally found in
the bank of the river in the middle of nowhere in מצרים.
Mitzrayim. He had a משגיח, mashgiach, though. He had a משגיח, mashgiach,
it's true. His sister was watching. You know, there's so many beautiful...
all the... the beginning of סוטה, Sotah, all of those מדרשים midrashim
about... about מרים Miriam watching over משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. It's very
interesting. מרים Miriam was what, six years old when she had her
נבואה nevuah that משה רבינו Moshe Rabbeinu would be born? And then
she contradicted her father, you know, lots of really interesting things going
on with... with מרים Miriam and משה, Moshe, their relationship. Obviously מרים
Miriam was always kind of watching over him, making sure he was
making the right decisions
also.
Well, but in the end it was for... for his benefit. Obviously
maybe she didn't say it the right way, but you know, she
was concerned. And of course the מפרשים, mefarshim, big מחלוקת of the
מפרשים mefarshim there. What is it she was disapproving of, right? It's
a מחלוקת whether she was disapproving of whom he married or whether
she was disapproving of the fact that he wasn't spending enough time
with his wife. So obviously two different important concerns there. Okay. So
וצידי רשות הרבים אין בו משום אסופי. ve'tzidei reshus harabim ein bo
mishum asufi. The edges of the public street doesn't count as an
אסופי asufi because again, that's a protected area. We saw in the
first פרק perek of מסכת שבת Masechet Shabbat that the... the edges,
that is the sidewalks or sort of right next to the storefronts
in רשות הרבים reshus harabim doesn't have the same status of רשות
הרבים reshus harabim as the middle of the street. So even though
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, sixteen אמה amah wide street,
is a רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, but the edges still have some
limitations on how it's... how they're treated. And that might be more
what we would call כרמלית, karmelis, that's already a rabbinically instituted רשות
הרבים. reshus harabim. So here too for אסופי, asufi, putting a baby
at the edge of the רשות הרבים reshus harabim is not really
considered to be putting the baby out in רשות הרבים, reshus harabim,
perhaps. The baby's not going to get trampled. If you put him
up against the wall by a storefront, there's less risk and therefore
that was a baby we were trying to protect. So if the
baby was found רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, really in רשות הרבים, reshus
harabim, יש בו משום אסופי. yesh bo mishum asufi. If he was
found in the middle of the street, obviously the baby was an
אסופי asufi because the baby was put there basically put there to
die. So אמר רבא Rava ובשני רעבון uvshanei raavon during years of
famine אין בו משום אסופי. ein bo mishum asufi. If you find
a baby during a year of famine, there's no concern about אסופי
asufi at all because the reason the baby was given up even
from a very good family is because they're starving and they need
to retain resources to save their other children. Obviously it's inexcusable to
leave a baby to die, I'm not trying to defend it but
just to get inside the mindset of the people who in that
situation felt that they were compelled to do that to save their
other children or to save themselves. It's at least understandable. So הא
דרבא אהי אילימא ארשות הרבים Ha d'Rava ahei? Ileima areshus harabim? So
that it sounds like it's even a better argument than saying from
רשות הרבים. reshus harabim. So once you say רבא, Rava okay, even
any inexcusable, understandable reason why this baby would be here and it
applies anywhere. Not just רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, not just anywhere, it
could be anywhere. So אידי ובשני רעבון קטלי ליה? Idei uvshanei raavon
katlei lei? So if it was in a famine year, so he
would have killed him, right?
It's very hot in here. One second. Okay. Okay. ואלא אצידי רשות
הרבים? Ve'ella atzidei reshus harabim?
So what is רבא Rava talking about? If the baby was put
into the middle of the רשות הרבים reshus harabim during a famine
and that's the only time you'd say אין בו משום אסופי, ein
bo mishum asufi, that is רבא Rava is being more מחמיר than
the previous line. So then ובשני רעבון uvshanei raavon so קטלי ליה?
katlei lei? So then you just you you should be that as
if to say that the goal was just they could have just
killed the baby. Okay. ואלא אצידי רשות הרבים? Ve'ella atzidei reshus harabim?
And if you're saying in a שני רעבון shanei raavon you would
say meaning he's being more מחמיר than the previous line, so מאי
איריא שני רעבון אפילו בלא שני רעבון? mai irya shanei raavon afilu
belo shanei raavon? So then the previous line said that on the
edge of רשות הרבים reshus harabim is not an אסופי asufi even
when it's not a famine. אלא כי איתמר דרבא אהא דאמר רב
יהודה אמר רבי אבא אמר רב יהודה, Ella ki itmar d'Rava aha
d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rabi Abba amar Rav Yehuda, so רבא Rava
was talking about this other opinion of רב יהודה בר זבדא אמר
רב: Rav Yehuda bar Zavda amar Rav: כל זמן שבשוק אביו ואמו
נאמנים עליו. kol zman shebashuk aviv ve'imo ne'emanim alav. The whole time
that he is in the שוק, shuk, that is while the baby
is still there, the parents if they show up and say 'no
no, that's our baby', the parents would be
believed. נאסף מן השוק אין נאמנים עליו. Ne'esaf min hashuk ein ne'emanim
alav. Then no longer are they believed that it's their child. That
is, at what point does the baby get the status or no
status of אסופי asufi but the parents could no longer come back
and claim him as their own? So in a year of famine,
what רבא Rava was saying is he's not called an אסופי asufi
because the parents could show up later and claim the baby. But
in a not in a year of famine, already as soon as
a baby would be taken back out of the שוק, shuk, then
the parents would no longer be believed. מאי טעמא אמר רבא הואיל
ויצא עליו שם אסופי, Mai ta'ama? Amar Rava: ho'il veyatza alav shem
asufi, because as soon as he's been called an אסופי, asufi, you
can't get rid of that שם. shem. That's like יצא קול. yatza
kol. As soon as everybody's heard about 'oh yeah, there was an
אסופי asufi found in the street, his name is Joe', so then
no offense Joe, so
then once the baby's been called an אסופי, asufi, you can't you
can't get rid of that name at that point. So the parents
couldn't show up and remove that status. ואמר רבא ובשני רעבון אף
על פי שנאסף מן השוק אביו ואמו נאמנים עליו. Ve'amar Rava: uvshanei
raavon af al pi shene'esaf min hashuk aviv ve'imo ne'emanim alav. So
רבא says if it was a year of famine, even after the
baby was taken in from the street, the parents could show up
and claim him and it would not be an אסופי. asufi. That
means what רבא is saying is that the אסופי asufi status once
it kicks in, once it's נאסף מן השוק, ne'esaf min hashuk, is
irreversible, but that's only in a year of plenty. But in a
year of famine, the parents could show up and reclaim the baby
after seemingly any amount of time presumably. I don't know, you know,
if there's a cutoff, a long-term cutoff. Years would be a major
question, but at least in the short term, perhaps a couple of
days or even a few weeks, the parents could show up later
and say 'no no, that was our baby'. It reminds you of
these, you know, after the Holocaust stories. Yeah, exactly, Holocaust stories for
sure. And you know, you hear about people, you know, 'I was
reunited with my sister, I was reunited with my aunt', and things
like that. It becomes really interesting questions of עריות arayos actually. There
are cases, someone falls in love with someone in a DP camp
and they trace it back and back and back and they find
out that they're aunt and nephew or they find that they're siblings
and then you have real עריות arayos questions. Yeah. And an example
from even further apart,
Trotsky's grandson who's halachically Jewish and still alive today
discovered that his sister had survived Stalin's purges in the late 1980s.
Oh wow. And he flew to he flew to Moscow to see
her as she was dying of cancer. Okay, so that's a big
deal. So let's see how far we can go in a few
more minutes.
We have a few more minutes. Okay, so we're right halfway down
on עין גמל עמוד ב. Ayin Gimmel Amud B. אמר רב חסדה
שלשה נאמנים לאלתר. Amar Rav Chisda: shlosha ne'emanim le'altar. There are three
types of people who are believed immediately, but meaning after any amount
of time. that is not immediately afterward, they would no longer be
believed. They're only believed in the moment. אלו הן: eilu hein: אסופי,
asufi, a case of אסופי, asufi, that is the parents of an
אסופי asufi can show up and say no, no, it was our
baby, חיה, chaya, a midwife who is delivering babies, ופוטרת חברותיה, upoteret
chavroseha, and a woman who is trying to
exempt other women of something. We're going to see what the ברייתא
braisa is talking about. So אסופי הדאמרן, asufi ha'adamran, the אסופי asufi
case we just talked about, that is this opinion of רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda that was quoted by רבא or qualified by רבא about
when is it that the parents would be believed that the child
is theirs. So whether he was נאסף מן השוק ne'esaf min hashuk
or not, that is whether the baby had been collected from the
marketplace yet or not, whether or not the baby has been called
an אסופי asufi or not, and רבא said we even would allow
the parents to show up even afterward if it had been a
year of famine, but in a normal case, they would only be
believed לאלתר, le'altar, immediately. So חיה דתניא, chaya detanya, a midwife as
we see in this ברייתא, braisa, חיה נאמנת לומר זה יצא ראשון
וזה יצא שני. chaya ne'emenes lomar zeh yatza rishon vezeh yatza sheini.
The midwife is believed about either two women giving birth or it
seems like the case that actually has a נפקא מינא nafka mina
is talking about in a case of two twins, which of the
twins is the בכור. bechor. So if there are two twin boys
being born and particular boys, you know we have the story of
תמר Tamar and יהודה, Yehuda, so תמר Tamar gave birth to two
twin boys and it was a complicated delivery such that the midwife
actually played a very important role in identifying who was the בכור.
bechor. So זה יצא ראשון וזה יצא שני, zeh yatza rishon vezeh
yatza sheini, ובמה דברים אמורים שלא יצתה וחזרה. uvamei devarim amurim shelo
yatzsa vechazra. It's only in a case where she did not leave
the birthing room and come back, אבל יצתה וחזרה אינה נאמנת. aval
yatzsa vechazra eina ne'emenes. But if she left the birthing room and
then came back, things could have gotten all mixed up while she
was gone. You know you hear all these stories, they switch two
babies, babies look very similar to each other when they're first born
and so there's not so much room, you know you could get
mixed up. Even a professional midwife could easily get confused. רבי אליעזר
אומר הוחזקה על עומדה נאמנת. Rabbi Eliezer omer huchzeka al omda ne'emenes.
If she's still sitting on the birthing stool, that's when she's believed.
ואם לאו אינה נאמנת. ve'im lav eina ne'emenes. And if she even
got up or turned her head or something like that, even then
she wouldn't be believed. So רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is even more
מחמיר than the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. So מאי בינייהו? mai beinaihu?
איכא בינייהו דאהדר אפי. ika beinaihu de'ahadar apei. In the case where
she turned her head or turned away from the woman giving birth,
in such a case רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say she's not
נאמנה ne'emana and the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would say that she
is נאמנה. ne'emana. So פוטרת חברותיה מאי היא? poteret chavroseha mai hi?
What case is פוטרת חברותיה, poteret chavroseha, a woman trying to exempt
her friends? דתנן, detnan, a משנה from נדה, Niddah, שלוש נשים שהיו
ישנות במיטה אחת, shalosh nashim shehayu yeshenos bemitah achas, there are three
women sleeping in the same bed. נמצא דם תחת אחת מהן, nimtza
dam tachas achas meihen, and there's blood found underneath one of them
or found in the bed. So כולן טמאות. kulan temeios. Then all
three of them are considered טמא tamei from ספק. safek That is
this sounds like a case of ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד safek tumah
birshus hayachid and therefore we have to say ספק טומאה safek tumah
that each one of these three women could have been נדה niddah
because of this. So בדקה אחת מהן ונמצאת טמאה. badka achas meihen
venimtzes teme'ah. If one of them performed a בדיקה bedika and found
out that she was טמאה, teme'ah, היא טמאה וכולן טהורות. hi teme'ah
vekulan tehoros. So she then would be considered נדה niddah and that
removes the ספק from the other two women. Leave it here but
just one point. The ראב"ד Ra'avad in בעלי הנפש Ba'alei Hanefesh talking
about the הלכות of doing בדיקות bedikos for נדה, niddah, the ראב"ד
Ra'avad contrasts the threshold, necessary threshold of proof, the burden of proof
for different types of בדיקות bedikos for נדה niddah and this case
to be פוטרת חברותיה poteret chavroseha is actually the lowest burden of
proof. That is even a minimal amount of proof, even a minimal
בדיקה, bedika, what the ראב"ד Ra'avad calls קינוח, kinuach, just wiping, but
not any kind of real internal בדיקה bedika is would be all
that's necessary in order to evaluate the believability in this case that
one woman and not the other two were נדה niddah because of
this.